Mss.497.43.V42
American Philosophical Society
Cakchikel Language Texts, 1553 - ca. 1700
Circa 1553-1700
Mss.497.43.V42
American Philosophical Society
10.0 Volume(s)
The library has several volumes of grammars, vocabularies, sermons, and other religious writings in the Cakchikel language of Central America. Several have been studied, notably by Daniel G. Brinton in APS Proceedings 21 (1884): 345, and Nora B. Thompson, "Algunos manuscritos guatemaltecos en Filadelfia", Anales de la Sociedad de Geografia e Historia 23 (1948), Nos. 1 2: p. 3; and all have been described by John F. Freeman, "Manuscript Sources on Latin American Indians," APS Proceedings 10 (1962): 530, and in Freeman's Guide to Manuscripts relating to the American Indian (1966).
10 volumes.
Academia de Ciencias de Guatemala..
Volume 1-10
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented by the Academia de ciencias de Guatemala, through Mariano Galvez, then Governor of Guatemala, and accessioned, 1836.
Existence and Location of Copies note
This collection is also available on microfilm (Film 1303).
Early American History Note
This manuscript collection falls outside the geographic scope of the Early American guide (British North America and the United States before 1840). It may be of interest to scholars interested in global history, international relations, imperialism, or the U.S. in the world.
Catholic Church -- Guatemala -- Catechisms -- Cakchikel.; Catholic Church -- Guatemala -- Sermons.; Coto, Thomás de, d. ca. 1656; Maldonado, Francisco; Saz, Antonio del.; Varea, Francisco de.; Cakchikel language; Grammars.; Indians of Central America--Languages; Mayan languages; Microfilm Collection; Sermons, Cakchikel.; Sermons.; Vocabularies.
- 1. Vocabulario de la lengua Cakchiquel y Guatimalteca, ca. 1700, Circa 1700; 497.43 C82; 1.0 Volume(s) 1 volume, 476 leaves; 1 volume, 476 leaves.; A vocabulary with illustrative examples from early writers; ethnographic data. No other copy known.; Coto, Thomás de, d. ca. 1656 (Volume 1)
  Immediate Source of Acquisition note
  Donor, Academia de Ciencias de Guatemala, through Mariano Galvez, 1836.
- 2. Doctrina christiana, 1692?, Circa 1692; 497.4 D65; 1.0 Volume(s); 1 volume, 110 leaves.; Sermons, catechism, religious discourses, and grammar of the Cakchiquel; the latter was translated into English by Daniel G. Brinton in APS Proceedings 21 (1884): 345. (Volume 1)
- 3. Arte, pronunciación y ortographia de la lengua ... cakchiquel, [ca. 1650], Circa 1650; 497.4 M29; 1.0 Volume(s) 1 volume, 79 leaves; A copy made in 1748 of Maldonado's "Ramilette" or anthology of 12 dialogues, together with a copy of an unknown "Doctrina Christiana" of 1556. Includes grammatical notes and vocabulary.; 1 volume, 78 leaves.; Maldonado, Francisco (Volume 1)
  General note
  Described in Daniel Brinton (1869), "Notice of some manuscripts in Central American languages," American Journal of Science series 2, 47: 222-230; and in Nora Thompson (1948), "Algunos manuscritos guatemaltecos en Filadelfia," Anales de la Sociedad de Geografia e Historia, Guatemala, ano 23, t. 23, no. 1-2, pages 3-10.
- 4. Libro de Sermones... Cakchiquel, 1647, 497.4 Sa9; 1.0 Volume(s) 1 volume, 373 pages; A book of Cakchiquel sermons.; 1 volume, 373 pages.; Saz, Antonio del. (Volume 1)
- 5. Manual de pláticas de todos los sacramentos para la administracion de estos naturales con otras cossas importantes (1664), 497.4 Sa9m; 1.0 Volume(s) 1 volume, 101 leaves; Includes 20 brief religious discourses; table of contents.; 1 volume, 101 leaves.; Saz, Antonio del. (Volume 1)
- 6. Sermón predicable en el domingo de septuagessima, 1727, 497.4 Se6; 1.0 Volume(s) 1 volume, 338 leaves; Sermons for holy days, the above being the title of the first volume.; 1 volume, 338 leaves. (Volume 1)
- 7. Uae nima vutz rij theologi aindox ubinaam nima (1553, 1605), 497.4 Ual3; 1.0 Volume(s) 1 volume, 185 leaves; Sermons in Cakchiquel, with marginal notes and birth records made by later missionaries. Includes table of contents.; 1 volume, 185 leaves. (Volume 1)
- 8. Uae rugotzlem Sant Andros apostol (1605), 497.4 Ual5; 1.0 Volume(s); Sermons.; 1 volume, 422 pages. (Volume 1)
- 9. Varea, Francisco de. Calepíno de la lengua Cakchíquel (1699), 497.43 V42; 1.0 Volume(s) 1 volume, 453 pages; Copy of dictionary of late sixteenth-century missionary made by Fray Francisco Ceron. 4,000 Cakchiquel words (Parra's orthography) with equivalents.; 1 volume, 453 pages. (Volume 1)
- 10. Vocabulario de la lengua Cakchiquel, ca. 1675, Circa 1675; 497.43 V85; 1.0 Volume(s) 1 volume, 717 pages; Cakchiquel dictionary (Parra's orthography).; 1 volume, 717 pages. (Volume 1)